Finding Aid for Charles Khalil Alawan papers, 1940-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Khalil Alawan papers 1940-2001
Alawan, Charles Khalil
0.5 linear ft. and 1 outsize folder
07112 Aa 2; UAm
Charles Khalil Alawan is a leader in the Arab American and American Muslim community of Southeastern Michigan, as well as a leader of the Michigan Republican Party. The collection documents the development of the Islamic Center of America, Dearborn, Mich., of which Alawan is a founding member, as well as other community activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Charles Khalil Alawan (donor no. 9887 ) in 2007.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles Khalil Alawan was born in Detroit in 1930, the son of Lebanese immigrants. He earned an engineering degree from Wayne University and served in the U.S. Army for six years in the 1950s. He became a successful businessman, working for Altair Industries, a Brighton, Mich., manufacturer, and later for Ansar Communications, a marketing firm.
During the 1950s Alawan was part of a group of young men in the Dearborn area who helped found what became the Islamic Center of America. Under the spiritual leadership of Imam Mohamad Jawad Chirri the Center grew to become one of the largest mosques in North America. Alawan was instrumental in attracting Mohammad Ali Elahi to the Center in 1991 to become imam after Chirri's retirement. Elahi went on to found the Islamic House of Wisdom in Dearborn Heights, Mich., in 1995.
Alawan has been active in the Michigan Republican Party, elected president of the Republican State Nationalities Council in 1967. He has been involved in a wide variety of interfaith activities, working especially to improve communication and understanding between the Muslim and non-Muslim communities in Michigan.
The papers of Charles Alawan document his work as a leader in the Arab American community in Southeastern Michigan as well as in the Republican Party of Michigan. The collection is divided into three series: Correspondence, Topical files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Alawan, Charles Khalil.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Elahi, Mohammad ʻAli.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.); Islamic House of Wisdom (Dearborn Heights, Mich.); Muslims--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.). Republican State Nationalities Council.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alawan, Charles Khalil.; Arab Americans--Egypt.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Egypt.; Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918-1970.; Thomas, Danny.
Contributors:
Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918-1970.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The correspondence series chiefly relates to Alawan's political activities, including exchanges of letters with political leaders and Republican Party activists at the state and national levels. Some correspondence concerning the development of the Islamic Center is also included. Of particular interest is a telegram (1959) confirming the transfer of over $40,000 donated by Egyptian president Gamal Abdel Nasser for the building of the Center, as well as a 1961 telegram from Nasser sending his best wishes to the Center.
  - 1959 (Box 1)
  - 1961 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1967 re Middle East war (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1992 (Box 1)
  - 1994 (Box 1)
  - 1996 (Box 1)
  - 1997 (Box 1)
  - 1998 (Box 1)
- Topical files
  The Topical files series includes files on various of Alawan's activities, noteworthy among them papers relating to the Boy Scout "In the Name of God" award for Muslim scouts (documents developed in part by Alawan), diversity and the portrayal of Arab Americans and Muslims in the Detroit Free Press and News, the arrival of Imam Elahi from Iran in 1991, and an early publication of the Progressive Arabian Hashmie Society (predecessor of the Islamic Center) on its 4th anniversary in 1940.
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Boy Scouts (Box 1)
  - Detroit Free Press and News, 1994-1997, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Detroit Historical Museums Arab American Advisory Committee, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Martin Luther King Award, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Guido, Michael, campaign literature (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center Foundation Society, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center of America, 1989-1999 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Center of America--Mohammad Ali Elahi, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Hospice Services, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Islamic House of Wisdom, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
  - Military intelligence (Box 2)
  - Muslim-American Perspective, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Progressive Arabian Hashmie Society, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Republican State Nationalities Council, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - Zogby American Muslim poll, 2001 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  Most of the photos in the Photographs series relate to Alawan's 1961 trip to Egypt and the Middle East with a delegation of Arab American community leaders. The photos document their activities, chiefly in Cairo but also in Alexandria, Gaza, and Damascus, including a meeting with President Nasser. The Photographs series also includes photos of Alawan at Republican Party and other gatherings, and an oversize photo of a large group including the Alawan family and many others (among them entertainer Danny Thomas) at a 1945 Detroit banquet honoring Syrian leader Ali al-Atrash.
  - Trip to Egypt and Middle East, 1961
    - Al Azhar University (Box 2)
    - Banquets (Box 2)
    - Damascus and Gaza (Box 2)
    - Nasser, Gamal Abdel (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous photos (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, (oversize folder UAm) (Folder UAm)